Anna H. Askanasy Papers, 1931-70
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Anna H. Askanasy papers
1931-1970
Askanasy, Anna H.
MS 7 UUID:462abbbb-165e-47eb-a233-d9f7ebe5eebb
2 boxes (1 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Author, Feminist. Correspondence, travel journals, and writings. Letters between Askanasy and archivist Margaret Grierson discuss social, economic, and political situation in the U.S. and Canada, 1950-70. Her journals and letters provide accounts of travels. Writings include her unpublished book, "The Catastrophe of Patriarchy."
Anna H. Askanasy was a Viennese woman who emigrated from Nazi Austria to Canada in 1938. Askanasy was involved in the women's movement and part of a circle of feminists which included Mary Beard and Rosika Schwimmer. She also appears to have been active in the movement for peace which emerged in response to the beginnings of the First World War. Askanasy's letters to Margaret Grierson, founder of the Sophia Smith Collection, reveal that she was deeply passionate about women's history and very interested in the potential of the Collection. Askanasy was an amateur women's historian herself and published a historical novel Empress of Byzantium (1952) under the pseudonym Helen A. Mahler. Her unpublished book, "The Catastrophe of Patriarchy," also reflects her interest in the subject.
The Anna H. Askanasy papers consist of one linear foot of correspondence, travel journals, and writings. The letters and cards exchanged by Askanasy and Margaret Grierson provide an engaging and insightful commentary on the social, economic, and political situation in the U.S. and Canada between 1950 and 1970. Askanasy's journals, like her letters, are not only colorful, vivid accounts of her travels around the world but powerful and historically contingent commentaries on her lived experience. Her writings reveal that she was a fiery, articulate and opinionated woman of the world.
This collection is organized into three series:
I. CORRESPONDENCE
II. JOURNALS
III. WRITINGS
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
History of the Collection
Anna H. Askanasy papers donated her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection from 1949 to 1970.
Search Terms
The following terms represent persons, organizations, and topics documented in this collection. To find additional materials use these headings to search this web site, the Five College Library Catalog, or other library catalogs and databases.
Askanasy, Anna H.; Canada--Description and travel--Sources; Europe--Description and travel--Sources; Mediterranean region--Description and travel--Sources; Middle East--Description and travel--Sources; Pro-choice movement--History--20th century--Sources; United States--Description and travel--Sources; Women historians--United States--Biography--Sources; Women--History--Historiography; Women's rights--Canada--History--Sources
Additional Information
Related Material
Additional papers of Askanasy are located at the Women's Library of the London Metropolitan University. Correspondence with Robert Briffault is kept with his collection at the William Ready Division of Archives and Research Collections at McMaster University Library Ontario, Canada. Letters to Mary Beard are held with the Charles and Mary Beard Papers in the Archives of Depauw University.
- SERIES I. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Letters, 27 Sep 1949-30 Jan 1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Christmas cards, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- SERIES II. JOURNALS
  - "Winter Journey to Hostile Countries" (United States, Europe, Middle East), 1959-60 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "My Mediterranean Journey" (United States, Europe), 26 Aug 1964-2 Jan 1965, 31 Mar 1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Journey in Search of My Lost Identity" (United States, Canada), Dec 1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Harvest Journey" (Europe, Canada), 10 May 1969-21 Jun 1969, 22 Jan 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- SERIES III. WRITINGS
  - Empress of Byzantium: brochure, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "The Catastrophe of Patriarchy" (Volume 1), undated (Box 1, Folder 8-12)
  - "The Catastrophe of Patriarchy" (Volume 2), undated (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
  - "Masculine Population Policy," 1931, revised 1937 and 1942 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
  - Articles
    - "Random Remarks About the Pending Abortion Reform Bill in Canada," undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Some Reflections Concerning the Status of Women," 25 Apr 1968 (Box 2)